{"tossups": [{"question": "In this state, the book<em> The Meritorious Price of Our Redemption</em> was burned for heresy; its author, William Pynchon, founded this state\u2019s town of Springfield. Edmund Andros was captured by rebels in what became this state in 1689, marking the end of the Dominion of New England. John Winthrop led a\u201cBay Colony\u201d named after this state, which contains the site where the Pilgrims aboard the<em> Mayflower</em> established the Plymouth Colony. For ten points, name this state where colonists founded the city of Boston.", "answer": "<b> Massachusetts</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This country established relations with Ethiopia\u2019s Dawit II after settling the Swahili Coast. To defend against this country, the Sultanate of Oman built the Old Fort in Zanzibar. After the collapse of its Estado Novo, this country relinquished its colonies in Angola and Mozambique. For ten points, name this country whose caravel ships explored the world under Vasco de Gama and Henry the Navigator.", "answer": "<b> Portugal</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "For ten points, name this legendary shortstop for the New York Yankees who retired in 2014.", "answer": "Derek<b> Jeter</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "During this battle, reinforcements sent down the Hagerstown turnpike dissolved almost immediately when commander Joseph Mansfield was shot. After heavy fighting at Miller\u2019s Cornfield, Dunker Church, and the Bloody Lane, the winning commander was criticized for failing to pursue his foes. The Emancipation Proclamation was issued shortly after this battle. George McClellan won at, for ten points, what 1862 battle in Maryland that proved to be the costliest single day in the Civil War?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Antietam</b> (accept Battle of<b> Sharpsburg</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In an attempt to assassinate this ruler, Giuseppe Fieschi constructed a 25 barrel volley gun known as the Machine Infernale. This man\u2019s Foreign Minister, Francois Guizot, fought with Lord Palmerston over the Spanish Queen Isabella II during the Affair of the Spanish Marriages. This King was frequently drawn as a pear by Honor\u00b4e Daumier [on-or-ay doh-me-ay]. This man came to power during the July Revolution and was overthrown in 1848. For ten points, name this French citizen king.", "answer": "<b> Louis-Philippe</b> I (prompt on \u201cCitizen King\u201d until mentioned) Page 1", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The author of this poem got his start composing literature when he saw a hunter kill a male crane in front of its mate. A woman in this poem uses one of two boons given to her by a king to order the king\u2019s son into a fourteen-year exile in a forest. A ten-headed figure in this poem abducts a woman and holds her captive on the island of Lanka. Hanuman aids the title character in rescuing his wife Sita in, for ten points, what Indian epic poem often compared to the<em> Mahabharata</em>?", "answer": "<b> Ramayana</b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "Kenneth Bianchi was arrested in 1979 for committing two murders in Washington and 10 murders in this state as the \u201cHillside Strangler.\u201d In this state, Elizabeth Short was murdered and her corpse severed in two in what became known as the Black Dahlia Murder. The symbol of a circle with a plus sign drawn through it was used by a murderer in this state who sent four ciphers to the police. For ten points, name this state where the Zodiac Killer terrorized San Francisco.", "answer": "<b> California</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A palace in this region contained the Moorish Hall and Hall of the Singers, though neither of those were finished once the king mysteriously died in the waters of Lake Starnberg. In this region, a hill overlooking Hohenschwangau village was the site of a fortress that inspired the Sleeping Beauty castle, Neuschwanstein [noysh-van-stein]. The \u201cMad King\u201d Ludwig II once ruled, for ten points, what German region whose capital is Munich?", "answer": "<b> Bavaria</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A Sangaku problem presented on a 1824 tablet in the Gunma prefecture concerns three of these shapes touching. These shapes were defined by Apollonius as the set of points in the plane that have a fixed ratio of distances to two foci. When Ferdinand von Lindemann proved that a certain constant is transcendental, he proved it is impossible to \u201csquare\u201d one of these shapes. Line segments between two points on them are called chords. For ten points, name these shapes that have a constant radius.", "answer": "<b> circle</b>s", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Math"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Recruitment posters for this war encouraging American soldiers to \u201cDestroy this mad brute!\u201d show an angry gorilla wearing a pickelhaube. During this war, which coincided with the Dada movement, John Singer Sargent painted blindfolded soldiers returning after being mustard gassed at the Battle of Ypres [eep]. The author of \u201cDulce et decorum est,\u201d Wilfred Owen, died in, for ten points, what war that lasted from 1914 to 1918?", "answer": "<b> World War I</b> (accept the<b> Great</b> War; accept the<b> War to End All Wars</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The Duke of Ormonde oversaw Britain\u2019s withdrawal from this war. After this war\u2019s Battle of Denain, one side recovered much of its losses under the command of the duc de Villars. The duc de Tallard\u2019s attempt to capture Vienna during this war was defeated at the Battle of Blenheim [blen-em]. The Duke of Marlborough and Eugene of Savoy commanded the winning alliance in this war against Louis XIV\u2019s army. For ten points, name this conflict that ended when Philip V was recognized as king of a certain Iberian country.", "answer": "War of the<b> Spanish Succession</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In this region, Romans established the colonies of Narbo Martius and Massalia. In the third century BC, a group of people from this region settled in the Anatolian region of Galatia. Led by Brennus, an army from this region sacked Rome in 387 BCE. An Arverni king from this region, Vercingetorix, fought the Battle of Gergovia and the Siege of Alesia against Julius Caesar, who wrote commentaries on his conquest of this region. For ten points, name this ancient region in modern-day France.", "answer": "<b> Gaul</b> (or<b> Gallia</b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man was banished to Avignon after Charles de Luynes caused the assassination of Concino Concini. This man allied France to Sweden via the Treaty of Barwalde in the</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>Thirty Years\u2019 War, countering Hapsburg power. This man, who defeated the Duke of</b> <b>Thirty Years\u2019 War, countering Hapsburg power. This man, who defeated the Duke of</b> <b>Buckingham in the 1627 siege of (*)</b> <b>Buckingham in the 1627 siege of (*)</b> La Rochelle, was targeted by Marie de Medici in the Day of the Dupes. For ten points, name this \u201cRed Eminence,\u201d an anti-Huguenot clergyman and chief minister to King Louis XIII [13th] who was succeeded by Cardinal Mazarin.", "answer": "Cardinal<b> Richelieu</b> (or Armand Jean du<b> Plessis</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "For ten points, name this state where the Cuyahoga River \u201coozes\u201d into Lake Erie after passing through Cleveland.", "answer": "<b> Ohio</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b>This country was the site of Operation Blue Bat, where Eisenhower sent 15,000 troops to help president Camille Chamoun end a religious war. To reduce ethnic conflicts in this country, its law mandates that its president must be a Sunni Muslim and its prime minister must be a (+) Maronite Christian. This country was invaded in 2006 after Hassan Nasrallah organized numerous cross-border ambushes against (*)</b> Israeli villages. For ten points, name this country where Hezbollah is based in Beirut.", "answer": "<b> Lebanon</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In this battle, the losing side\u2019s defensive lines were planned by engineer Richard Gridley. The third and final assault on the losing side\u2019s redoubt led to the deaths of both John Pitcairn and Joseph (+) Warren, and forced Isaac Prescott to withdraw from Charlestown. During this battle, Israel Putnam legendarily told his troops (*)</b> not to fire until they saw the whites of their enemies\u2019 eyes. William Howe was victorious in, for ten points, what costly 1775 battle outside Boston fought near Breed\u2019s Hill?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Bunker Hill</b> Page 9", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Robert Morrison\u2019s translation of the Bible hastened the spread of Christianity in this country. The Nestorian Stone tells of how the monk Alopen traveled to this country, which</b> <b>was also visited by the Jesuit Matteo (+)</b> <b>Ricci. The Three-Self Church was set up in this</b> <b>country when its communist party came to power in the early (*)</b> 1950s. For ten points, name this country where Christianity was suppressed under the Cultural Revolution.", "answer": "<b> China</b> (accept People\u2019s Republic of<b> China</b> after \u201cThree-Self\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Miguel de la Madrid was criticized for not allowing foreign aid after one of these events. The deadliest of these events in modern history struck Tangshan, China in 1976. The Marquis of Pombal cemented his power by rebuilding (+) Lisbon after one of these events</b> <b>in 1755 caused widespread fires and a (*)</b> tsunami. Sixty-three people died in 1989 after one of these struck near Loma Prieta on the San Andreas fault. For ten points, name these natural disasters, one of which devastated San Francisco in 1906, that are commonly followed by deadly aftershocks.", "answer": "earth<b>quake</b>s ", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>The founder of this empire allegedly took power by using a rooster spur-tipped</b> <b>arrow to slay his rival. This kingdom\u2019s territories were divided into the \u201cTwelve</b> <b>Doors.\u201d (+)</b> <b>Askia Mohammad I led this empire to its military height. The Songhai</b> <b>Askia Mohammad I led this empire to its military height. The Songhai</b> <b>supplanted this empire, whose most famous ruler allegedly (*)</b> <b>supplanted this empire, whose most famous ruler allegedly (*)</b> devalued gold with his lavish gift-giving during a hajj to Mecca. Mansa Musa led, for ten points, what West African empire, home to Timbuktu?", "answer": "<b> Mali</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}